<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cases considered and resolved. Wherein all the tender godly conscientious ministers in England (whether for a Congregationall, or a Presbyteriall way) are concerned. Or pills to purge malignants. And all prophane, ignorant, and scandalous persons. (But more particularly calculated for the meridian of Margarets Fishstreet-hill) from those grosse conceits that they have of their childrens right to baptisme; and of their owne right to the Supper of the Lord, &amp;c. Also good councell to bad men. Or friendly advise (in severall particulars) to unfriendly neighbours. By Thomas Brooks, a willing servant unto God, and the faith of his people, in the glorious Gospel of Christ, at Margarets Fishstreet-hill.</title>
            <author>Brooks, Thomas, 1608-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4938</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E684_28</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207067</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866139</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866139</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118403</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77605)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118403)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 105:E684[28])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cases considered and resolved. Wherein all the tender godly conscientious ministers in England (whether for a Congregationall, or a Presbyteriall way) are concerned. Or pills to purge malignants. And all prophane, ignorant, and scandalous persons. (But more particularly calculated for the meridian of Margarets Fishstreet-hill) from those grosse conceits that they have of their childrens right to baptisme; and of their owne right to the Supper of the Lord, &amp;c. Also good councell to bad men. Or friendly advise (in severall particulars) to unfriendly neighbours. By Thomas Brooks, a willing servant unto God, and the faith of his people, in the glorious Gospel of Christ, at Margarets Fishstreet-hill.</title>
                  <author>Brooks, Thomas, 1608-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 26, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Simmons, for John Hancock and are to be sold at the first shop in Popes-Head-Alley, next to Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "Jan. 18.th. 1652"; the "3" in the imprint has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pastoral theology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118403:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CASES <hi>CONSIDERED</hi> and <hi>RESOLVED.</hi> WHEREIN All the tender godly conſcientious Miniſters in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (Whether for a Congregationall, or a Presbyteriall way) are concerned. OR <hi>Pills to Purge Malignants.</hi> And all prophane, ignorant, and ſcandalous perſons. (But more particularly Calculated for the Meridian of <hi>Margarets</hi> Fiſhſtreet-hill) from thoſe groſſe conceits that they have of their Childrens right to Baptiſme; and of their owne right to the Supper of the Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ALSO Good Councell to bad men. Or friendly adviſe (in ſeverall particulars) to unfriendly Neighbours. By THOMAS BROOKS, a willing Servant unto God, and the Faith of his People, in the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, at <hi>Margarets</hi> Fiſhſtreet-hill.</p>
            <q>Mallem ruere cum Chriſto, quam regnare cum Caeſare. <bibl>
                  <hi>Luther.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Si veritas est cauſa diſcordiae, mori poſſum tacere non poſſum. <bibl>
                  <hi>Jerome.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>M. Simmons,</hi> for <hi>John Hancock</hi> and are to be ſold at the firſt Shop in <hi>Popes-Head</hi>-Alley, next to Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118403:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118403:2"/>
            <head>To the Conſcientious READER.</head>
            <p>THe World is full of Books, and of how many may it be ſaid, That they doe but proclaim the vanity of the writer, and procure wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe, if not vexation, to the Reader, in this knowing and cenſorious age? What I have written is out of faithfullneſſe to Chriſt, and love to Souls: If my pains ſhall prove advantageous, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and eternall good of any poor Souls, I ſhall count it reward enough. I doubt not but thoſe that are ſpirituall will find ſomething of the Spirit in what followes, and for that cauſe will relliſh and love it, though others may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtand at the greater diſtance from it. Surely, where Truth comes, the Children of Truth will entertaine it, and aske no body leave. In theſe dayes they that have leaſt right to Ordinances, doe make the greateſt noiſe in crying out for Ordinances. Gods Ordinances are choice pearles, and yet too often caſt before Swine, which doubtleſſe hath provoked the Lord to ſhed the blood of many among us, who have unworthily drunk the blood of his Son, and trampled it under their feet as an unholy thing.
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> Though my Candle be but little, yet I muſt not hide it under a buſhell. Though
<pb facs="tcp:118403:3"/>I have but one Talent, yet I muſt not hide it in a Napkin. I hope thou haſt that anointing of the Spirit that will teach thee not to reject the fruit for the trees ſake, nor ſo much to mind the man as the matter. But leaſt I ſhould hold thee long in the porch, I will briefly acquaint thee with the Reaſons that have induced me to preſent to the World what followes; and ſo draw to a cloſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Reaſons are theſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the honour, truth and wayes of Chriſt, which I hope are dearer to me then my life,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note> and which are ſtruck at thorow my ſides, may be vindicated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the mouth of iniquity (or which is all one,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 107.42. Titus 1.11. Pſal. 63.11.</note> that the foule mouths of prophane, ignorant, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant, and ſcandalous perſons) may be effectually ſtopt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That the honeſt, juſt, and righteous proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Honourable Committee may be manifeſted, and not ſmothered by the falſe reports of any prophane malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſpirits that were preſent;
<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.20.</note> who are apt and ready e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to call good evill, and evill good, light, darkneſſe, and darkneſſe light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That the importunate deſires of ſeverall Miniſters, and Chriſtians may be ſatisfied, eſpecially thoſe to whom I preach, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11. Ch. 10-ult. Pro. 22.1. Eccleſ. 7.1.</note> That my Miniſtry and good name (which ſhould be dearer to me then my life) may be vindicated. A good name is rather to be choſen then great riches, and loving favour rather then ſilver and gold: a good name is better then precious ointment, ſaith <hi>Solomon, Eccleſ. 7.1.</hi> The initiall letter (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) of the Hebrew word (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tob</hi>) that in this Text is rendred good, is bigger then ordinary, to ſhew the more then ordinary excellency of a good name amongſt men. The Moraliſts ſay of fame, or of
<pb facs="tcp:118403:3"/>a mans good Name <hi>(Omnia ſi perdas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The French have this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb among them, That a good renown is better then a golden Gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle.</note> 
               <hi>famam ſervare memento; Qua ſemel amiſſa poſtea nullus eris) i. e.</hi> Whatſoever commodity you loſe, be ſure yet to preſerve that Jewell of a good Name. But if any ſhall delight to blot and blur my name, that their owne may ſhine the brighter; I ſhall deſire them frequently to remember a ſweet ſaying of <hi>Auſtin (Quiſquis volens detrahit famae meae, nolens addit mercedi meae.)</hi> He that willingly takes from my good Name, unwillingly addes to my reward.
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.11.12.</note> The remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of this, and the bird in the boſome (conſcience) ſinging, makes a Heaven of joy in my heart,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.12.</note> in the middeſt of all the trialls that doe attend me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> That others may be undeceived, who are apt enough to judge that there are other things and worſe things charged upon me then indeed there is.
<note place="margin">Jer. 20.10, 11. Pſal. 35.11.</note> And indeed ſome ſay already, that there were eighteen things, others that there were ſix and twenty things charged against me; and all this to render my perſon and my doctrine, contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible in the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> That the Malignant and profane Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and others of their ſtamp, may be either ſatisfied, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, and reformed, or that they may be found ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and without excuſe in the day of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eightly,</hi> Becauſe my caſe is a generall caſe, and reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es all the godly conſcientious Miniſters in <hi>England,</hi> be they of one judgement or another. And clearly if upon the following Charge against me, the prophane, ignorant, and Malignant party, ſhould out and rout the godly Miniſters in the Nation; I wonder where there would be found a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Miniſter, that ſhould not upon theſe grounds be outed and routed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118403:4"/>
            <p>I deſire that thou wouldeſt caſt a mantle of love over the Miſtakes of the <hi>PRINTER,</hi> I having no opportunity to wait on the Preſſe, by reaſon of my many Engagements other wayes. I will not by any Prolepſis detaine thee at the doore, but deſire that the God of all conſolations would bleſſe thee with all externall, internall and eternall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, that thy actions may be proſperous, thy troubles few, thy comforts many, thy life holy, thy death happie, and thy ſoule lodged for ever in the boſome of Chriſt. So I remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine, ſo farre as thou art CHRISTS.</hi> Thomas Brooks.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:118403:4"/>
            <head>A <hi>SHORT PREAMBLE That I intended (to make before the Honourable Committee for Plundred Miniſters) that Truth and my Selfe might be the better vindicated and cleared.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>'TWas a Divine ſaying of <hi>Seneca,</hi> No man ſets a better rate upon vertue,
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Qui boni viri famam perdidit ne conſcientiam perderet.</hi> Seneca.</note> then he that looſeth a good Name to keep a good Conſcience. He that hath a good conſcience, ſits <hi>Noah</hi>-like, quiet and ſtill in the greateſt combuſtions, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions <hi>(Conſcientia pura ſemper ſecura)</hi> A good Conſcience hath ſure confidence, it makes a man as bold as a Lyon, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs</hi> 28.1.</p>
            <p>I remember <hi>Calvin</hi> writing to the French King, ſaith, that Oppoſition is <hi>(Evangelij genius)</hi> the black Angel that doggs the Goſpel at the heels. And certainly, where Chriſt is like to gain moſt, and Satan like to loſe moſt, there Satan in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments will ſtir and rage moſt; yet if every oppoſer of the Goſpel and the Saints, were turned into a Devil, that old ſaying would be found true <hi>(Veritas ſtat in aperto campo)</hi> Truth ſtands in the open fields, yea and 'twill make thoſe ſtand in whom it lives; yea 'twill make them ſtand chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, reſolutely, and unmoveably, in the face of the greateſt, higheſt, and hotteſt oppoſitions.</p>
            <p>Concerning theſe prophane, ignorant, malignant, and ſcandalous Petitioners, I ſhall ſay as <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſaith of <hi>Lucian (Nec diis nec hominibus pepercit)</hi> he ſpared neither God, nor
<pb facs="tcp:118403:5"/>man; ſuch are theſe Petitioners. 'Tis ſaid of <hi>Cataline,</hi> that he was
<note n="b" place="margin">Monſtrum ex variis diverſiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inter ſe pugnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus naturis conflatum.</note> a compound and bundle of warring luſts and vices; ſuch are theſe Petitioners. Hiſtorians ſay, that Tygers rage and are mad, when they ſmell the fragrancy of Spices; ſuch are theſe Petitioners, when they ſmell the fragrancy of the Graces of Gods Spirit in the principles and practices, in the lives and religious exerciſes of the people of God.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, I am compelled to tell you that I have by the gracious aſſiſtance of God, preached publiquely the Goſpel above theſe thirteen years, and the greateſt part of thoſe years I have ſpent in Preaching the word in <hi>London,</hi> where God hath given me many precious ſeals of my Miniſtry, which are now my comfort, and in the day of Chriſt will be my Crown. They are my living Epiſtles, they are my walking Certificates, they are my letters teſtimoniall, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks. And yet in all this time none have ſhewed themſelves ſo malicious,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.1, 2.</note> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent and ignorant, as to Petition againſt me, as theſe that ſtand now before you; yet am I confident that this act of theirs ſhall work for my externall, internall, and eternall good:
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28. Judg. 14.14.</note> And out of this eater God will bring forth meat and ſweetneſſe to others alſo.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, I ſhall now trouble your patience no further but come now to anſwer to the things that theſe prophane, Malignant Petitioners have charged againſt me, in their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to this Honourable Committee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:118403:5"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE COMMITTEE <hi>FOR</hi> Plundred Miniſters. The humble Petition of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners of <hi>Margaret New-Fiſhſtreet, London,</hi> whoſe Names are hereunto ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</head>
            <opener>SHEWING,</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat one Mr. <hi>Thomas Brooks,</hi> was by Order of your Honours, dated the twenty third of <hi>March,</hi> 1651. appointed to Preach for a Moneth, next enſuing, as Probationer; to the end, that upon the Pariſhioners, and the ſaid Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> mutual tryal of each other, the ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:118403:6"/>Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> might continue, or your Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners have ſome other to officiate amongſt them.</p>
            <p>Your Petitioners are humbly bold to offer to your Honours conſideration, that they have had tryal of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> ever ſince your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours Order; but cannot finde that comfort to their ſoules they hoped; nor indeed is the ſaid Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> ſo qualified to your Petitioners underſtandings, as to remain any longer with them. And further, your Petitioners ſay, that the ſaid <hi>Mr. Brooks</hi> refuſeth to afford your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners the uſe of the Ordinances, of Baptiſm and the Lords Supper; nor will he bury their dead.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>The Petitioners therefore humbly pray, that your Honours will be pleaſed to revoke your Order, and give liberty to your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners for ſix Moneths, to preſent a fit perſon to your Honours to be their Miniſter; and in the mean time, that Sequestrators may be appointed to provide for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Cure, out of ſuch money, as ſhall ariſe for tithes out of the ſaid Pariſh; And,</hi> &amp;c.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="queries">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118403:6"/>
            <head>QUERIES Upon the Malignants PETITION.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N their Petition they ſay, that I was to preach a Moneth, as Probationer, and after a mutual tryal of each other, I might continue, or the Petitioners have ſome other to officiate amongſt them. To this I ſay,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That I never had any ſuch thing, by one or other propounded to me, to preach amongſt them as Probationer. It was onely thus propounded to me; That at a full meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I was choſen by the honeſt and well affected of the Pariſh, to come and preach amongſt them. And I did more then twice or thrice declare to them before I came, that if they did expect any thing elſe of me, I would not come: Onely I did declare my willingneſſe, to receive any among them into Fellowſhip with us, that the Lord had taken into Fellowſhip with himſelf, and that were willing to walk in Goſpel-order.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſay, that had they propounded the buſineſs to me, as tis preſented in their Petition, I would never have come upon ſuch terms, and that upon ſeveral reaſons, which here, I ſhall omit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſay, that they had a tryal of me all the Winter, I preached above twenty Sermons on the Lecture-nights, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118403:7"/>this Order was granted, or deſired; therefore I know not to what purpoſe I ſhould preach among them upon tryal, when they had before-hand ſo large a tryal of me.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I ſay, that theſe prophane, malignant Petitioners, had neither a hand in chuſing of me, nor yet hearts to make any tryal of my miniſtry; (ſo far as I can underſtand) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they may well have a black brand put upon them, as men void of common honeſty and ingenuity, in abuſing the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Committee, and petitioning againſt me: When as they were neither the major part of the Pariſh, by far, nor yet was the Order of the Committee granted to them, nor did the Order of the Committee give any power, or liberty to theſe prophane malignant Petitioners, to chuſe ſome other to offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate, as they pretend; what greater diſhonour and contempt can they caſt upon the Committee, then to declare to the world, that they have given to them (that are ſo notoriouſly known for their prophaneneſs and malignancie) an Order to chuſe one to officiate amongſt them.</p>
            <p>In their Petition they further ſay, That they have had tryal of me ever ſince your Honours Order; this is as far from truth, as the Petitioners are from being real friends to the preſent Authotity of the Nation. For tis notoriouſly known, that they uſe not to hear me, but others, whoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant principles and practiſes, are moſt ſutable to their own.</p>
            <p>Further they ſay, they cannot finde that comfort to their ſoules they hoped. Here give me leave to quere; 1. How they could have any comfort from my miniſtry, that did not attend it. 2. But grant they did, I Quere, whether their want of comfort, did not ſpring rather from their want of faith, to cloſe with the word, and to feed upon the word, and to apply the word to their own ſoules, then from any defect in my preaching? <hi>The word preached did not profit them, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mixed with faith, in them that heard it,</hi> Heb. 4.2. Faith and the word meeting, make a happy mixture, a precious confecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. When faith and the word is mingled together, then the word will be a word of power and life; then 'twil be a heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing word, a quickning word, a comforting word, a ſaving
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118403:7"/>word. Faith makes the ſoul fruitful;
<note place="margin">As <hi>Luther</hi> ſaith of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſo I may ſay of ſaith, it hath a kind of Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency in it, 'tis able to do all things. <hi>Eſt quaedam omnipotentia precum. Tantum poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, quantum credimus.</hi>
               </note> faith hath <hi>Rachels</hi> eye, and <hi>Leahs</hi> womb. Where faith is wanting, mens ſouls will be like the Cypreſs, the more it is watered, the more it is withered. However that tree that is not for fruit, is for the fire, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.8. Some ſay of King Midas, (not true, but fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous) that he had obtained of the gods, that whatſoever he touched ſhould be turned into gold. I may truly ſay, in a ſpiritual ſenſe, what ever faith touches, it turnes it into gold, into our good. A Bee can ſuck hony out of a flower, ſo can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not a Flie do. Faith will extract abundance of comfort out of the word, and gather one contrary out of another, honey out of the rock, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.36.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I quere, whether their not finding comfort by my mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, did not rather ſpring from a judicial act of God,
<note place="margin">When ſhe in <hi>Seneca,</hi> was ſtricken with ſudden blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhe cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the light: So when God ſtrikes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane men with ſpiritual blindneſſe, then they cry out of the Miniſter, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.70.</note> rather then from any thing in my miniſtry? God, many times, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes mens neglect of the means, and their diſpiſing the means, and their barrenneſs under the means, &amp;c. by giving them up to a ſpirit of ſlumber, by ſhutting their eyes, and cloſing up their hearts, as you may ſee in that, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.9, 10. and he ſaid, <hi>Go and tell this people; hear ye indeed, but underſtand not, and ſee ye indeed, but perceive not; Make the heart of this people fat, and make their ears heavy, and ſhut their eyes; leſt they ſee with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and underſtand with their heart, and convert and be healed.</hi> A fat heart is a fearful plague; a fat heart is a moſt brutiſh and blockiſh heart; a heart fitted and prepared for wrath. Theſe four keyes (ſay the Rabbins) God keeps under his own girdle: 1. The key of the womb. 2. The key of the grave. 3. The key of the rain. 4. The key of the heart. <hi>He openeth and no man ſhutteth, and he ſhutteth and no man openeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. I Queere, whether their not finding of comfort did not ſpring from the wickedneſs and baſeneſſe of their own hearts, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.13, 14. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33, 30. - <hi>ult. Mat.</hi> 15.4, - 10.
<note place="margin">The Patient in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> complained to his Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an of his Finger, when his Liver was rotten. So many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the Miniſter, when their hearts are rotten; they complainthey can finde no comfort, when the fault lyes in the baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their hearts,</note> When men bring pride, and prejudice, and refolvedneſſe to walk after the waies of their own hearts, let the miniſter ſay what he will, (as they in <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> 44.15. - <hi>ult.</hi> which I deſire you will turn too and read) tis no wonder, that they can finde no comfort in the word. This is juſt as if the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118403:8"/>ſhould cry out of the Phyſician, Oh he can finde no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in any thing he preſcribes him; when he is reſolved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand, that he will rather dye then follow his preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. May not every one of theſe mens hearts ſay to him, as the heart of <hi>Apollodorus</hi> in the Kettle (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) 'tis I have been the cauſe of this? I judge they may, and if they will not now acknowledg it to their humiliation, they will at laſt be forc'd to acknowledg it, to their confuſion and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in that day wherein the great ſearcher of hearts ſhall judge the ſouls of men.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I Quere, whether all the godly conſcientious Miniſters, of one judgement or another, in all England, would not be outed and routed, if this plea of prophane, ignorant, malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.8.-29.</note> and ſcandalous perſons, that they cannot finde no profit, nor no comfort by their miniſtry, be admitted, as a thing that has worth or weight in it. Without doubt, if this would carry the day againſt a godly miniſtry,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.16</note> we ſhould hear a cry from all parts of the Nation, where ſuch men are; Oh! what ſhall we do with ſuch Preachers as theſe be?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.8, 9, 10, 11.</note> we can finde no comfort, nor no profit by their miniſtry; we will have none of theſe, but we will have ſuch, as will preach pleaſing things;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.14.</note> we will have Common-prayer-book men, and ſuch that will adminiſter Sacraments to us, as in former good dayes, wherein their was no ſuch difference put between men and men, but all that would bring their two-pences, might come and be as welcome to the Parſon, (if not more) as any Puritan, or Round-head of them all.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I Quere, whether your not finding of comfort and profit by the word, did not ſpring from Satans blinding your eyes, and from his catching away the good ſeed out of your hearts. <hi>If our Goſpel be hid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3, 4. Satan is like the picture of the Goddeſſe, that was ſo contrived, that ſhe frown'd on men as they went into the Temple, and ſmil'd as they came out. <hi>Math.</hi> 13.19. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Rapio,</hi> He took it, or ſnatch't it by force or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. </note> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>it is hid to them that are loſt: Whom the god of this world hath blinded the minds of them which believe not, leſt the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the image of God, ſhould ſhine unto them.</hi> Is it any wonder, that prophane, ignorant, ſcandalous perſons, can finde no comfort by the word, when as the Devil hath ſhut their eyes with his black hand? When he hath put a covering upon their eyes, that they can't ſee any beauty, excellency, or glory in it?
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118403:8"/>Goſpel droppings have richly fallen among many, and yet like <hi>Gideons</hi> fleece they are dry, becauſe Satan has blinded them, and catched away the good ſeed that was ſowen upon them. <hi>When any one heareth the word of the Kingdom, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth it not, then cometh the wicked one, and catches away that which was ſowen in his heart:</hi> (or rather upon his heart) <hi>this is he which received ſeed by the way ſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. I Quere, whether your want of profit and comfort by the word, did not ſpring from your want of intereſt in Goſpel-conſolations.<note place="margin">'Tis intereſt in a pardon, a Crown, an inheritance that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, and not the talking of them: So here. The very Heathen could not have comfort, nor quiet when they were under the rage of ſinful luſts; therefore when they knew not how to bridle them, they offered vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: pulling out their own eyes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they could not look upon a woman, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out luſting after her. </note> Oh, 'tis not the hearing of Goſpel-conſolations that comforts, but the knowledg of a mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in them that cheers up the heart. Ah, where is that word to be found in all the Book of God, that does evidence comfort, (which is childrens bread) to be of right belonging to prophane, ignorant, malignant, and ſcandalous perſons, as you can't but know your ſelves to be, if conſcience be in the leaſt meaſure awakned. God hath all along in the Scripture, made a ſeperation between ſin and comfort; and how then can you expect comfort, who hold on in ſinful wayes? though love and wrath, life and death, heaven and hell, be often ſet before you. God is not prodigal of Goſpel-conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations: they are the beſt, and ſtrongeſt Wines in Gods Cellar, and reſerved onely for his beſt and deareſt friends, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.1.2. <hi>Comfort ye, comfort ye my people, ſaith your God, ſpeak ye comfortably to Jeruſalem, and cry unto her, that her warfare is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, that her iniquity is pardoned,</hi> &amp;c. The Hebrew word that is here rendred <hi>comfort,</hi> ſignifies firſt to repent, and then to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. And certainly, the ſweeteſt joy is from the ſowreſt teares. Tears are the Breeders of ſpiritual joy: When <hi>Hannah</hi> had wept, ſhe went away and was no more ſad. The Bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the beſt honey of the bittereſt hearbs: Chriſt made the beſt wine of water. The pureſt, the ſtrongeſt, and moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent joy, is made of the waters of Repentance. Ah, lay your hands upon your hearts, and tell me, whether you can look God in the face and ſay, Lord we are thine; Firſt, by Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe. Secondly, we are thine by Choice. Thirdly, we are thine by Conqueſt. Fourthly, we are thine by Covenant. Fifthly, we are thine by Marriage.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>nahhamu, nuhhamu,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>nahham;</hi> which ſignifies, firſt, to repent, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.35. and then to comfort, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe true comfort be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs only to the penitent. Divine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate thing, and it is not given to him, that admits any other, ſaith <hi>Bernard. Nulla verior miſeria quam falſa loetitia.</hi> Bernard. There is no truer miſery then falſe joy. <hi>Nil niſi ſanctum a ſancto Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu prodire poteſt.</hi> Neh. 8.10. There have been thoſe that have died under the ſtrength and power of their joy. <hi>Valde proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſum, me nolle ſic ſatiari ab eo. Luther.</hi> I ſaid ſtatly, that God ſhould not put me off with theſe low things. I have read of one who cried out with a loud voice to <hi>Flavius Veſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſianus, (vuſpem pilum mutare non mores)</hi> that the Wolfe might change his hair, but not his quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. You know how to apply it. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49.4, 5.</note> Ah, if you are not the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118403:9"/>Lords in theſe reſpects, what Miniſter on earth hath a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to comfort you? their commiſſion is to read other Lectures to prophane, ignorant, ſcandalous perſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then thoſe of comfort and joy, as you may ſee in theſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, (if you will but take the pains to read them) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.5, 6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.10, 20. compared with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.20. <hi>Job</hi> 21.30. <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.5, 21, 31. compared, <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.19. <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.29. <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.18, 27. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 25.31. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.18, 19. <hi>Nah.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.15-<hi>ult. Levit.</hi> 26.14-<hi>ult.</hi> Ah, did you but wiſely conſider the excellency of Goſpel-comforts, above all other comforts in the world, you would not wonder at Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters giving them forth ſo ſparingly, to prophane, ignorant, malignant, and ſcandalous perſons: For firſt, Goſpel-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts are unutterable comforts, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.4. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they are real, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.27. all others are but ſeeming com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, but painted comforts. Thirdly, they are holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.5. they flow from a holy Spirit, and nothing can come from the Holy Spirit, but that which is holy. Fourthly, they are the greateſt and ſtrongeſt comforts, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.17. few heads and hearts are able to bear them, as few heads are able to bear ſtrong wines: Fifthly, they reach to the inward man, to the ſoul, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.17. the noble part of man: <hi>My ſoul rejoyceth in God my Saviour.</hi> Our other comforts onely reach the face, they ſinck not ſo deep as the heart. Sixtly, they are the moſt ſoul-filling, and ſoul-ſatisfying comforts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. <hi>ult. Can.</hi> 2.3. other comforts cannot reach the ſoul, and therefore they can't fill, nor ſatisfie the ſoul. Seventhly, they comfort in ſaddeſt diſtreſſes, in the darkeſt night, and in the moſt ſtormie day, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.19. <hi>Hab.</hi> 3.17, 18. verſes. Eightly, they are everlaſting, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.16. The joy of the wicked is but as a glaſs, bright and brittle, and evermore in danger of breaking, but the joy of the Saints is laſting. <hi>(Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terna erit exultatio, quae bono laetatur aeterno)</hi> Their joy laſts for ever, whoſe object remains for ever.</p>
            <p n="8">8. I Quaere, whether you, and men of your ſtamp (remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the power of your luſts) will ever ſay, that you can finde any comfort at all in any mans miniſtry, that is not a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118403:9"/>Common-prayer-book man, or one that will give you and yours the Sacraments, and laſh at the power of godlineſſe, and at the State, in preaching, and praying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doubtleſſe under ſuch a mans miniſtry (were he never ſo ignorant, ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous or prophane) you would plead that you found much comfort, to your ſouls, and that he was a man indeed for your money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Well, if you have found no comfort, under my miniſtry, yet my comfort is, that my reward is with the Lord, and my work with my God: my comfort is, that there are many hundreds in this City, that have, and that do finde comfort, by the bleſſing and breathings of God upon my weak endeavours.</p>
            <p>Further, in their Petition they ſay, that I am not ſo quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to their underſtandings, as to remain any longer with them.</p>
            <p>To this I ſay, Firſt, 'tis my joy and crown, that I am not ſo qualified, as to pleaſe and content, ignorant, prophane, malignant, ſcandalous perſons in their formality, and impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Remembring that he is the beſt Preacher,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non qui aures tetigerit, ſed qui cer pupige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Male de me lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur, ſed mali,</hi> ſaith <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca.</hi>
               </note> not that tickles the ear, but that breaks the heart. 'Tis a comfort to me that I am no neerer that woe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.26. <hi>Woe be to you when all men ſpeak well of you.</hi> When one told <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> that he had every mans good word; ſaith he, what evil have I done, that I ſhould have every mans good word? 'Tis ſometimes more a ſhame then an honour, to have the good word of prophane, ignorant, ſcandalous perſons. <hi>Latymer</hi> in his laſt Sermon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore King <hi>Edward,</hi> ſaith, That he was glad when any objected indiſcretion againſt him in his Sermons; for by that he knew the matter was good, elſe they would ſoon have condemned that. 'Twas a notable ſaying of <hi>Salvian,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mirum eſſet ſi hominibus lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentia de Deo verba, non pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceant quibus ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe forſitan Deus non placet,</hi> Salv.</note> 'Twere very ſtrange, (ſaith he) If I ſhould pleaſe a world of men, when God himſelf, doth not give every man content. <hi>Luther,</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to his friend, hath this paſſage, My greateſt fear is the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of men, but my joy is in their reproaches and evill ſpeeches. 'Tis certain that the praiſes of men, to many, are the Baſilisks, that kill, the poyſon that deſtroyes their immortal ſouls.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſay, If the underſtandings of ignorant, malignant, prophane and ſcandalous perſons, ſhould be the rule or ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118403:10"/>by which the abilities, or qualifications of ſuch Miniſters, that are Miniſters, <hi>not of the letter, but of the ſpirit,</hi> (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaks) ſhould be meaſured and tried:
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.</note> doubtleſſe he that is no Witch may eaſily conclude, that there are no Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.30, 31.</note> qualified to their underſtandings, but ſuch as are malignant, ignorant, prophane, and ſcandalous as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and ſuch without doubt would be the onely qualified men to their underſtandings; as might be confirmed by a cloud of witneſſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriyſoſtom</hi> ſtudied not, <hi>(aures titillare,</hi> but <hi>corda pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere)</hi> to tickle the ears of his hearers, but to prick and raviſh their hearts. <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.30.</note> Though I am not qualified, as to their underſtandings, yet (through grace) I am qualified, as to the underſtandings of thoſe, that are eminent both for piety and parts, and who have made tryal of what is in me, and what the Lord hath done for me. And though I am not ſo qualified, as to gratifie your luſts, yet tis joy and honour enough to me, that the Lord hath ſo qualified me with gifts and grace, as to make me inſtrumental, to bring in ſouls to Chriſt, and to build up ſouls in Chriſt. In the day of account it will be made manifeſt, that they have been the beſt, the wiſeſt, and ableſt Preachers, who have brought moſt ſouls to Chriſt, and provok't moſt ſouls to walk with Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>velokeakh.</hi> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies by art and induſtry, to catch ſouls, as Fowlers do to take birds.</note> and cleave to Chriſt, and lift up Chriſt in this world. Through grace, I can ſay, (with bleſſed <hi>Cooper</hi>) my witneſſe is in heaven, that I have no ſuch joy, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as in doing the work of Chriſt, and in being ſerviceable to the honour of Chriſt, the intereſt of Chriſt, and the people of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If this plea of prophane, ignorant, malignant and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous perſons ſhould be admitted, as authentick, doubtleſſe, all the godly,
<note place="margin">They that are wiſe cannot but obſerve much of this ſpirit, upon all the prophane, ignorant, and malignant perſons in the Nation.</note> tender conſcientious Miniſters in the Nation, that can't do as they would have them, would quickly be ejected. All the prophane, ignorant, malignant, ſcandalous perſons in the Nation, would ſoon cry out, as one man, Our Miniſters are not ſo qualified to our underſtandings, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main any longer with us, <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. 'Tis to be remembred, that when the Petitioners were ſeveral times preſt by the Committee, to ſhew wherein I was not qualified for the work of the Miniſtry,
<note place="margin">The Petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſeemed to be like thoſe in <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.46. that were non pluſt, by the queſtion Chriſt put to them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> My firſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preached before the Parliament, was on the 26. Decmb. 1648. My ſecond was preached on the 8. of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, 1650. for that great vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, the Lord of Hoſts gave our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my over the <hi>Scots</hi> Army, in a barttel at <hi>Dunbar,</hi> Sept. 3. 1650. and both are prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their Order. Beſides my book, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Precious Renedies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Satans devices;</hi> which came forth this year which ſome of them have ſeen.</note> they all ſeemed to be dumb, and at very great loſſe, as not knowing what to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118403:10"/>anſwer; but at laſt, their malignant Champion, after much pumping gave this anſwer to the Committee, That I was not ſo qualified to their underſtandings, as to remain any longer among them; becauſe I would not give them the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, nor bury their dead; which put ſome rather upon ſmilings, then upon anſwering. But at laſt a worthy Member of that Committee, made this anſwer, That they had both heard me and ſeen me in Print, and ſo were beſt able to make a judgement of my abilities, and fitneſſe for the work of the Miniſtry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For a cloſe of this branch of the Petition, I ſhall onely ſay this, (being compelled thereunto by ſome) that I do believe, that I have ſpent more money at the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and in helps to Learning, then ſeveral of theſe Petitioners are worth: (though haply I have not been ſo good a profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, as thoſe that have ſpent leſſe) I am a lover of the Tongues, and do, by daily experience, finde, that knowledg in the Original tongues, is no ſmall help for the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Scripture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet am I not kin to them, that advance and lift up acquired gifts, above the ſweet ſanctifying gifts and graces of the Spirit of Chriſt, in the ſouls of his Saints, as many have, and do to this day. But certainly Chriſt will more and mote, cloud thoſe that labour to cloud the ſhinings forth of his Spirit, in the ſouls of his ſervants. Nor yet am I kin to <hi>Licinius,</hi> who held Learning to be the Common wealths Ratsbane. Neither am I kin to thoſe, that labour might and main the overthrow of Learning, in order to their lifting up <hi>Jack Straw.</hi> 'Tis ſad, when men are not ſo ingenious, as to favour that in others, which they can't finde in themſelves.</p>
            <p>Further, the Petitioners ſay, that I refuſe to Baptize their children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. This give me leave to premiſe by the way, that tis my judgement,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38, 39. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> (upon many grounds moving me to it) that Baptiſm is to be adminiſtred to the children of believing Parents, who walk in the order of the Goſpel; and my practiſe herein, doth anſwer to my judgement, as is well known to many.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But in the ſecond place, I confeſſe I have refuſed, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118403:11"/>ſhall refuſe to Baptize the children of prophane, ignorant, malignant and ſcandalous perſons, and that upon theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing grounds.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Non parentum aut majorum authoritas, ſed Dei docentis imperium,</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom. The command of God, muſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weigh all au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and example of men.</note> Becauſe I cannot finde any warrant in my commiſſion from Chriſt ſo to do. I do ſeriouſly profeſſe, that I have made a diligent ſearch and ſtrict inquiry into that commiſſion, that I have received from the Lord, for the diſpencing of holy things; and I cannot finde any thing in my commiſſion that will bear me out, in the Baptizing the children of thoſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents that are prophane, ignorant, malignant, ſcandalous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore I cannot do it, leſt I ſhould hear Chriſt and conſcience, ſounding that ſad word in my ears; <hi>Who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired this at your hand?</hi> Iſai. 1.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe, ſuch perſons that are prophane, ignorant, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.5, 6, 7, 8, 9.10, 11, 12. <hi>Mark.</hi> 1.4, 5. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38, 41. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.3. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.24. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.12, 31. to the end. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.45, 46, 47, 48. <hi>Acts</hi> 18 8. <hi>Acts</hi> 22.16, 17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So <hi>Pſ.</hi> 50.16, 17.</note> ſcandalous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if they were now to be baptized themſelves, ought not to be baptized, they having no right to baptiſm, as theſe Scriptures in the margent do evidence: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch Parents cannot juſtly, upon any Scripture account, chalenge baptiſm for their children, who have no right to it themſelves. All that know any thing are not ignorant of this, that tis the Parents intereſt in the Covenant that gives the child right to baptiſm; now how prophane, ignorant, ſcandalous parents, can give their children right to baptiſm when they have no right to it themſelves, is a thing that I am no wayes able to reach; and a thing (I judg) too hard for any to prove <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.2, 3.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe, the children of Parents, whereof neither can be judged, to be a Believer, ought not to be Baptized, till the child grow up to manifeſt his own faith, as theſe Scriptures (among many others that might be produced) prove, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 8, 9. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.39, 40, 41. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.15, 18. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> They cut a covenant with hell &amp; death: in old time men were wont to kill and cut aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſacrificed beaſts, and to paſſe between the parts di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, <hi>Gen</hi> 15.17. <hi>Jer.</hi> 34.18. The cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, that he might be cut in pieces, as that beaſt was, who ſhould vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſo made. The ſame rite was uſed among the heatheniſh Gentiles alſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23.</note> Becauſe, prophane, ignorant, ſcandalous perſons, &amp;c. are viſibly in covenant with Satan, and therefore to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter baptiſm, the ſeal of the Covenant to their children, upon their accounts who are viſibly in Covenant with Satan, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be a notorious prophaning of the Ordinance, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I dare not do it. Now that ſuch perſons are viſibly in Covenant with Satan is clear, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 28.15. <hi>Becauſe ye have ſaid,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118403:11"/>We have made a covenant with death, and with hell, are we at agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when the overflowing ſcourge ſhall paſſe through, it ſhall not come unto us; for we have made lyes our refuge, and under falſhood have we hid our ſelves,</hi> verſ. 18. <hi>And your covenant with death ſhall be diſanulled, and your agreement with hell ſhall not ſtand; when the overflowing ſcourge ſhall paſſe through, then ye ſhall be trodden down by it.</hi> Not that they had formally made a covenant with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan; but their waies and courſes were ſuch, as did proclaim to the world, that they had as it were formally made a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with hell and death. Therefore to apply this bleſſed Ordinance to their children, who are thus inviſibly in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with Satan; and who are not capable thereof, through want of divine warrant, cannot (doubtleſſe) but be eſteemed a high prophaning of it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Becauſe, I may not yield blind obedience, nor do any thing doubtingly, both which I ſhould do, ſhould I baptize their children, who are prophane, ignorant, ſcandalous, mockers, and ſcoffers, at God and godlineſſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Becauſe, by adminiſtring that holy Ordinance to the children of prophane, ignorant, ſcandalous perſons, I ſhall make my ſelf guilty, of nouriſhing,
<note place="margin">If I partake in other mens ſins, I muſt partake in their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. Chriſtians were wont to be of that courage, that they feared nothing but ſin. <hi>Nil niſi peccatum timeo,</hi> ſaid <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi>
               </note> and cheriſhing in ſuch wicked perſons, ſuch vain opinions and conceits, that cannot but be very prejudicial to their ſouls, as that they have aright to that precious ordinance, when they have none. That God hath taken their children into covenant, as well as the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the beſt believers in the world, when he hath not. That God is more favourable and loving to them, then indeed he is: And that their caſe is not ſo bad as ſome would make it, &amp;c. All which opinions and conceits (with many more of the ſame ſtamp that might be named) cannot but prove many wayes prejudicial to mens immortal ſouls.</p>
            <p>I ſhall forbear the laying down any more reaſons, why I have not, nor ſhall not baptize their children, who are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, ignorant, malignant, ſcandalous, mockers, and ſcoffers at God and godlineſſe; judging that theſe may be ſufficient, to ſatisfie all intelligent men.</p>
            <p>Further, theſe Petitioners ſay, that I will not give them the Lords Supper.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118403:12"/>
            <p>Anſw. Though I do give the Lords Supper to thoſe to whom of right it belonges, yet I cannot, I dare not give it to prophane, ignorant, malignant, ſcandalous perſons. I had, with <hi>Calvin,</hi> rather dye, then that this hand of mine ſhould give the things of God to the contemners of God.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14. <hi>ult. Phil.</hi> 32. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.26. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12, 13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15, 21, 27. It is worſe to admit a man openly pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſins, then a man bodily poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> The <hi>Thurians</hi> had a law, that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh an old law ſhould preſent himſelf with a rope about his neck, before the people; that if his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention was not approved, he might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently be ſtrangled. You know how to apply it. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27, 28, 29, 30. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.12, 13, 14, 15, 16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 21, 22. compared, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.18, 19.</note> And with <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> I had rather give my life to a murderer, then Chriſts body to an unworthy receiver. And had rather to ſuffer my own blood to be poured out like water, then to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſts bleſſed blood to any baſe liver, and that upon theſe following grounds.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe, ſuch perſons are excluded by the word of God, from communion with Believers in that glorious Ordinance, as the Scriptures in the margent do evidence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Not onely the Scriptures, but the very Epiſcopal Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, for the adminiſtration of the Communion, dos exclude, and ſhut out ſuch perſons from the ſupper of the Lord, in theſe words, <hi>They that intended to partake of the holy Communion, ſhould ſignifie their names afore to the Curat and if any of thoſe be an open and notorious evil liver, ſo that the Congregation is offended; or have done any wrong to his neighbour by word or deed, the Curat having knowledg, ſhall call him and advertiſe him in any wiſe, not to preſume to the Lords table, until he hath openly declared himſelf, to have truely repented, and amended his former naughty life, that the congregation may thereby be ſatisfied,</hi> &amp;c. As for the Presbyterial way, you all know, that by their Directory, and lawes annexed, they muſt not receive any to the Communion that are ignorant, ſcandalous or prophane in their converſation. So that the ſumme of what hath been ſaid is this, that by the lawes of God, and by the lawes of Epiſcopacy, and by the lawes of Presbyterie, prophane, ignorant, and ſcandalous perſons are to be excluded from the Supper of the Lord. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe, the admitting of ſuch that are prophane, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, ſcandalous, or that are ſcoffers, and mockers of all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c. to the Supper of the Lord, is the ready way to turn the Houſe of God into a den of theeves; and to bring a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful doom, both upon conſenters, and preſumers, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the margent will make good. Not onely the lack of the word and Sacraments, (ſaith <hi>Bilſon</hi>) but the abuſe of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118403:12"/>either greatly hazards the weal of the whole Church. If prophane ones be allowed to defile the myſteries and aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the faithfull, and holy things be caſt to doggs,
<note place="margin">Matth. 7.6.</note> it will procure a dreadfull doom, as well to conſentaries as preſumers. <hi>Ergo,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe there are many horrid ſins in their coming to the Supper of the Lord.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 There is horrid pride,
<note place="margin">Yet pride cannot climb ſo high, but juſtice will ſit above her.</note> elſe no man in his wickedneſſe would preſume to taſt of the Tree of Life.</item>
               <item>2 There is Rebellion and Treaſon againſt the Crowne and Dingity of Chriſt. Their hands and lips adore him, as <hi>Judas</hi> his did, but their hearts and lives abhor him.</item>
               <item>3 There is theft and ſacriledge,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Poſſidonius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, that all that took the gold of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſe,</hi> periſhed in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it. Apply it. They may ſay with <hi>Henry</hi> the 7th, the cup of life is made my death.</note> if the taking away of the Communion Cup or Cloath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be ſuch horrible theft and ſacriledge, ſurely, it is far greater theft and ſacriledge to take that bread and wine that is ſet apart, and ſanctified by the Lord himſelfe, for a holy uſe.</item>
               <item>4 There is murther in the cruelleſt manner that can be; for they kill two at once, Chriſt, and their own ſouls, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27.29. compared.</item>
            </list>
            <p>'Twas wickedneſſe in <hi>Julian</hi> to throw his blood in the face of Chriſt; but for a wicked Communicant to take Chriſts own blood (as it were from his heart) and throw it into the face of Chriſt, is moſt abominable and damnable.</p>
            <p n="5">5.
<note place="margin">A gracious ſoul may ſay, not only (<hi>Credo vitam aeternam &amp; edo vitamaeternam</hi>) I believe life eternall, but I receive life eternall.</note> They want thoſe qualifications that ſhould fit them for this glorious Ordinance. As,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Experimentall knowledge.</item>
               <item>2 Faith, without which they cannot ſee Chriſt, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt, nor feed upon Chriſt, nor apply Chriſt, nor ſeale to Chriſt.</item>
               <item>3 Repentance from dead works.</item>
               <item>4 New obedience.</item>
               <item>5 Love to Chriſt and his Children.</item>
               <item>6 Holy thankfulneſſe.</item>
               <item>7 A ſpirituall Appetite. All which are abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to fit ſouls for the Lords Supper, <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="6">6. Becauſe ſuch as are prophane, ſcandalous, ſcoffers,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118403:13"/>and mockers,
<note place="margin">Read theſe Scriptures. <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.14, 15, 16. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9, 10, 11. 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. The Heathen could ſay <hi>(Qui aequo ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo malis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcetur, malus eſt)</hi> He that is well content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to keep company w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> thoſe that are naught, is himſelf made naught. <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 25. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19, 20. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15, 16, 17, 18. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not fit for civil ſociety, how much leſſe fit are they then for Religious ſocieties? Men that love but their names and credits in the world will ſhun the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of ſuch vain perſons; how much more then, ſhould men that love their Chriſt, and that love their precious ſouls, ſhun ſuch ſociety? Look as ſhelves and ſands do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the Sea-man, and as weeds endanger the corne, and bad humours, the blood, and an infected houſe, the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood: So does the ſociety of evill men, endanger good men. One ſaid, <hi>As oft as I have been among wicked men, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned home leſſe a man then I was before.</hi> Men that keep ill company, are like thoſe that walk in the ſun, tanned inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly. <hi>Euſebius</hi> reports of <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt, that he would not ſuffer <hi>Cerinibus</hi> the Heretick in the ſame Bath with him, leſt ſome judgement ſhould abide them both. You may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apply it to the point in hand.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Becauſe ſuch perſons as are prophane, ſcandalous, and wicked, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if they were in the Church, they are by the word of God to be Excommunicated, and cut off from viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble union and communion with Chriſt and his Church; therefore they are not to be admitted to the priviledges of the Church. That wickedneſſe that is a ſufficient ground for the caſting them out if they were in, is a ſufficient ground to keep them out from polluting the glorious Ordinance of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="8">8.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.27, 28, 29. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16, 17, <hi>&amp;c. Mat.</hi> 3.12.</note> Becauſe the Supper of the Lord is a Feaſt inſtituted by Chriſt only for his friends and children, for thoſe that have received ſpirituall life from him, and that have union and communion with him. But prophane, ignorant, malignant, ſcandalous perſons,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 15 8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6, 7.</note> are chaffe which the fan flings out of the floor. They be as dirt and duſt which the beſome ſweeps out of the houſe. They be as leaven, which if let alone, ſo wres the whole lump, and therefore muſt be purged out. They be as thorns and briers which muſt not ſtand in the middeſt of the corne,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.7.</note> but muſt be ſtub'd up and burned. They be as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Sepulchres, out of which proceeds nothing but noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſavours.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 28.3, 4, 5.</note> They be as Vipers, which muſt be ſhook off, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſhook off the Viper that faſtned upon his hand. They
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118403:13"/>be as ravenous wolves, which every carefull,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 10.12.</note> watchfull ſhepheard muſt keep out of his fold. They be as ſwine, that will trample the choiceſt pearls under their feet,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.6.</note> if they ſhould be caſt before them; therefore Miniſters muſt not hang Goſpel-pearls in ſuch ſwines ſnouts,
<note place="margin">The Table of the Lord (ſaith <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi>) is that whereon the (bleſſed) car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſe is laid; we muſt not ſuffer chatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Jaies to come there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, for only high-flying Eagles are to feed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon.</note> nor caſt them under ſuch ſwines feet. The fouler the cheſt is, the more unfit it is to have a fair and precious Garment put therein; and the filthier the ſoule is, the unfiter it is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in this holy Sacrament. I have read of a Jewel, that being put into a dead mans mouth, loſeth all its vertue. Such a Jewell is the Supper of the Lord, it looſeth its vertue when 'tis put in prophane, ignorant, ſcandalous perſons mouths, who are dead God-wards, and dead Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-wards, and dead Holyneſſe-wards, and dead Chriſt-wards.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, theſe Petitioners ſay, That I will not bury their dead.</p>
            <p>To this I ſhall give this ſhort Anſwer, That if they mean that I would bury their dead after the old faſhion,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.22. Nay, 'tis known to hundreds, that 'tis my practice, after the dead is buryed, to preach to the people that are met upon that occaſion (if ſo deſired) many grounds moving me thereunto.</note> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it, and ſhall only ſay, that 'tis moſt proper for the dead to bury the dead, as Chriſt ſpeaks; my work being to Preach the Goſpel. But if by burying their dead, they mean, that I wil not accompany their Corps to the grave, being the laſt office of love that can be performed to the deceaſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, 'tis notorious falſe; all that know any thing of the Scripture, can't but know that there is nothing in all the Book of God that will bear a Miniſter out to bury the dead, as prophane, ignorant, ſcandalous perſons, would have them buried; and therefore I don't, and I hope I ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſo far left of God, as to conform to the ſuperſtitious deſires and cuſtoms of vain men.</p>
            <p>Reader, for a cloſe, thou mayeſt take notice, That though I was ready to give in the fore-named Arguments,
<note place="margin">Greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Committee could not caſt upon me, nor greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon the prophane malignant Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners, then not to put me to anſwer to the things ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt mee. One of theſe prophane ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to me, <hi>Judas</hi> his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Supper of the Lord, which I diſproved, &amp; yet this vain; perſon (as I have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd) boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of victory. <hi>John</hi> 13.30. <hi>Hilar Durand. Piſcator, Beza, &amp;c.</hi> compare <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. and <hi>Mark.</hi> 14. to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and you ſhall find that neither of them doaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> was at the Lords Supper, therefore we have no ground to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> was at that bleſſed Supper. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19, 20. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26, 27, 28, 29.</note> in anſwer to the objections made by the Prophane Malignants, in their Petition againſt me. Yet the Committee in their wiſdomes (it ſeems) did not judge it meet ſo much as to ask me a reaſon, why I did not Baptize their Children, give them the Lords Supper, and bury their dead: they well knowing,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118403:14"/>that there is nothing more ordinary, then for thoſe to be bauling and crying out for Ordinances, that have no right to them: And that if upon the non giving of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances to ſuch prophane perſons, they ſhould eject Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters out of their places, they ſhould quickly eject all thoſe in the Nation, that are moſt tender of the honour of Chriſt, and that have been ſome of their beſt friends in the worſt times.</p>
            <p>Before I give the Councel intended to the Petitioners, I judge it uſefull (in ſeverall reſpects) to batter downe that which moſt prophane, ignorant, malignant, ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous perſons doe count their ſtrong hold, or their greateſt Argument to prove it lawfull for them to receive the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord, notwithſtanding their prophaneneſſe and wickedneſſe; and that is, <hi>That Judas was admitted to the Lords Supper, and that they are not worſe then Judas, no nor yet ſo bad, Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the caſting downe of this their (imagined) ſtrong hold, for the diſpatching this their firſt born, this their <hi>Goliah,</hi> conſider with me theſe following things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Holy Ghoſt by the Evangeliſt <hi>John,</hi> doth punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and expreſly tell us, that <hi>Judas</hi> went out immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the ſop. That this ſop was no part of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Supper, both Fathers and School-men doe agree, and many others in our own time, who are men of great piety and parts, <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did I know any thing of weight that could be objected againſt this Argument, I would be ſo faithfull as to give an anſwer to it, as the Lord ſhould inable me to doe, but I know nothing that ha's that ſtrength in it, as to weaken the truth aſſerted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe to whom Chriſt gave the Sacrament, he ſaith without exception, <hi>This is my body which is given for you; this is the cup of the new Teſtament, in my blood, which is ſhed for you; and I will not drinke henceforth of the fruit of the Vine, untill that day I drinke it new with you in my Fathers Kingdome.</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118403:14"/>Now I would willingly know,
<note place="margin">Were hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates known to us, we ought to ſhut the door againſt them, and will Chriſt open it? ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no.</note> how this can in the leaſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſtand with the wiſdom, holineſs, juſtice, righteouſneſs, innocency, and integrety of Chriſt, to ſay this, and promiſe this to <hi>Judas,</hi> whom he knew to be an hypocrite, reprobate, a devil, as himſelf calls him? <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.70, 71. <hi>chap.</hi> 13.10, 11. If this be not to make Chriſt a falſe witneſſe, a lyer, a decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I know not any thing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis as clear as the Sun, (from that 22. of <hi>Luke</hi> 28, 29, 30.) that thoſe to whom Chriſt gave the Sacrament, were ſuch as did continue with him in his temptations,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.24. <hi>Mark</hi> 14.21. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.70. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.25. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2, 3.</note> and ſuch as Chriſt did appoint to them a kingdom, and ſuch as ſhould ſet upon Thrones, &amp;c. Now are there any ſo vain and fooliſh, as to ſay, that <hi>Judas</hi> did continue with him in his temptations? Or, that Chriſt did appoint to him any other kingdom, then a kingdome of darkneſſe? Or, that he ſhall ſet on a Throne to judge others, who ſhall at laſt be judged as a Devil?</p>
            <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quod non acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ſed finibus penſantur officia.</hi> Duties are eſteemed not by their acts, but by their ends.</note> 
               <hi>Judas</hi> was no wayes capable of any of thoſe noble ends and glorious uſes, for which the Lord Jeſus appointed this Sacrament; he having no real love to Chriſt, no experimental knowledge of Chriſt, no faith to diſcern Chriſt, to apply Chriſt, to feed upon Chriſt, to ſeal to Chriſt, &amp;c. How could this Ordinance ſtrengthen grace in his heart, who was wholly void of grace? How could this Ordinance confirm him in the love of God, who was at that very time under the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt wrath of God?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Maximilians</hi> Motto, was <hi>Tene menſuram, &amp; reſpice fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi>
               </note> How could this Ordinance ſeal up to him the pardon of his ſins, who notwithſtanding all the hell fire, that Chriſt caſt in his face, yet would hold on in his ſins, and rather betray Chriſt into the hands of his enemies, and his own ſoul into the hand of Satan, then ceaſe from doing wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, &amp;c. That little wiſdom that is in man, will work him to forbear his work, and ſuſpend his act,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.3.</note> where he ſees his end will fail. And will not thoſe treaſures of wiſdome that be in the Lord Jeſus, much more work him to ſuſpend his work, where he ſees plainly and cleerly that his end will fail him? (as in the caſe of <hi>Judas</hi>) ſurely it will.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Conſider ſeriouſly, whether it be in any degree pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that Jeſus Chriſt would give his blood to <hi>Judas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 17.9.</note> and yet not ſo much as lift up a prayer for <hi>Judas;</hi> that Chriſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118403:15"/>would do the greater thing for <hi>Judas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sanguis Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, clavis coeli.</hi> Chriſts blood is heavens key. And ſo Judas would have found had Chriſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it to him.</note> and yet not doe the leſſer; that he ſhould give his blood to <hi>Judas,</hi> and yet not ſpend a little of his breath, to ſave <hi>Judas</hi> from wallowing in his blood for ever. Among men, it would argue the greateſt weakneſſe that could be, to deny the leaſt favour, where they have ſhewed the greateſt favour, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Well, but if for argument ſake we ſhould grant, that <hi>Judas</hi> did receive the Lords Supper, it will not from thence follow, that tis lawful for thoſe that are openly prophane, wicked, ſcandalous, and malignant to receive it, and that upon theſe following grounds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Secreta mea mecum.</hi> My ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret is with my ſelf, is an Hebrew Proverb. We are not to look to mens hearts, but to their lives and converſations, and according as they are good or bad ſo to proceed.</note> For that <hi>Judas</hi> was a cloſe hypocrites and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his ſin ſo ſecretly, that nothing appeared openly againſt him, for Chriſt yet to refuſe him. Hypocriſie is ſpun of a fine thred, and not eaſily diſcerned, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.21, 22. And as they did eat, he ſaid, <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, that one of you ſhall betray me: And they were exceeding ſorrowful, and began every one of them to ſay unto him, Lord is it I?</hi> Sincere hearts, are more jealous of themſelves then of others; and will rather judge a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand hypocrites to be Saints, then one Saint to be an hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 2. Becauſe <hi>Judas</hi> was a member of the Church, and had done nothing openly that could caſt him out; and by vertue of this memberſhip, he might juſtly claim it as his due, he being called into fellowſhip by Chriſt himſelf. Now what advantage is this, to ſuch open prophane wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as (<hi>de jure</hi>) ought and (<hi>de facto</hi>) are excluded from the Lords Supper, as I have before cleerly and fully proved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 3.
<note place="margin">Judas, as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> thinks, was pretty ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt till he carried the bag. (It is hard to be in office, and not to put conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence out of office) Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were of <hi>Tertullians</hi> opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Judas, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.1, 2. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.21. <hi>Cato</hi> hits M. <hi>Caelius</hi> in the teeth with this baſeneſſe, that for a morſel of bread, hee would ſell ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his tongue, or his ſilence. <hi>Iſa</hi> 53.2, 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.30, 31. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.20, 21, 22, 23. <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.21. <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.3, 4, 5. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.20.</note> Becauſe, in reſpect of wickedneſſe and all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſſe, they go beyond <hi>Judas, Judas</hi> was no drunkard, ſwearer, mocker, ſcoffer, he did not ſin openly, and glory in his ſin. He did not by any open way of wickedneſſe, ſad and quench Chriſt his Spirit, or Diſciples: he was ſo far from giving any ſcandall, or offence to his fellow-Diſciples, that when Chriſt told them, <hi>one of you ſhall betray me,</hi> they were all jealous of themſelves, none of them were jealous of <hi>Judas; And they began every one of them to ſay unto him, Lord, is it I?
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118403:15"/>Judas</hi> betrayed Chriſt for thirty pieces of ſilver, but open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane wicked perſons, they betray Chriſt, his word, his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and their own ſouls for a thing of naught. They will tranſgreſſe for a morſel of bread, (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks) for a trifle. They will fell the greateſt and the choiceſt things dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheap, even at the pooreſt and the loweſt rate, that the world, or the god of this world ſhall bid. <hi>Judas</hi> betrayed Chriſt once, and open prophane wicked perſons, by their open trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and tranſgreſſions, do oftentimes in a day betray the Crown, Scepter, and dignity of King Jeſus. <hi>Judas</hi> plotted treaſon againſt Chriſt when he was in a low afflicted, deſpiſed condition; but ſuch as are openly prophane, and wicked, they plot and act treaſon againſt Chriſt, now he is exalted, crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſet down at the right-hand of God, in that glory and Majeſty, that can neither be conceived nor expreſſed by any mortal creature. <hi>Judas</hi> betraies Chriſt, and is ſtruck with dreadful horror and terror, but ſuch as are openly wicked, they betray Chriſt, and yet joy in their tranſgreſſions, which are as ſo many treaſons againſt Chriſt. <hi>Judas</hi> betrayes Chriſt, and yet juſtifies the innocency of Chriſt, he repents and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth his ſin; but ſuch as are openly wicked, proceed from evil to evil, and yet with the harlot, they wipe their mouthes, and ſay, What evil have we done?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 4. Becauſe,
<note place="margin">Had Chriſt, as a God and ſearcher of the heart, kept out Judas from the Paſſover, becauſe he knew his heart was naught, he had left us a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern to eject ſuch as the Church ſhould be jealous of, that their hearts are not right before the Lord, when there is nothing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected.</note> Chriſt gave the bleſſed Sacrament Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterially, as he was man, leaving them a pattern to walk by that ſhould come after him; and ſuch was the carriage of Chriſt toward <hi>Judas</hi> all along. Chriſt did not act toward <hi>Judas</hi> as he was an all-ſeeing God, nor as he was the heart-maker, the heart-ſearcher, the heart-obſerver, the heart-diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer, but he acted towards him miniſterially. Neither do I ſee how it could ſtand with the holineſſe, juſtice, faithfulneſſe, and wiſdom of Chriſt, to give that holy Ordinance to <hi>Judas,</hi> whom he knew (as he was God) to be ſuch a dog, a devil, conſidering how he had bound all his ſervants from caſting pearls before ſwine. To affirm that Chriſt gave the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to <hi>Judas,</hi> as he was God, what is this, but to make Chriſts practiſe, fight againſt his own precepts? which for any to do, is, doubtleſſe, blaſphemy in the higheſt degree.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118403:16"/>
            <p>And now I appeal to the conſciences of all prophane, wicked, malignant perſons, whether they were not better a thouſand times, to be ſhut out from this glorious Ordinance of the Lords Supper, (till the Lord ſhall in mercy, if it be his good pleaſure, fit them for it) then to think to get in at this door, by making <hi>Judas</hi> the Porter.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now adreſſe my ſelf, to give ſome good counſel to the Petitioners, and ſo conclude.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:118403:16"/>
            <head>GOOD COUNCEL TO Bad Men. OR <hi>FRIENDLY ADVICE</hi> TO Unfriendly Neighbours, and their Abettors.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OUR Petitioning againſt me, to all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding men, was a compounded evil; an evil made up of pride, envy, malice, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, ignorance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan</hi> 4.27. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 50.11. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 33.14. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam ubique de gehenna diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reretur,</hi> Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom. I could wiſh that men would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe much and oft of hell.</note> My councel to you is to breake off your ſins by repentance, that it may go well with you for ever; if you will not, juſtice will be above you, and in the cloſe, you muſt lye down in ſorrow. Tell me, Can you dwell with the devouring fire? Can you dwell with everlaſting burnings? 'Twas a good ſaying of <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> ſpeaking of hell, (<hi>Ne quaeramus ubi ſit, ſed quomodo illam fugiamus</hi>) Let us not ſeek where it is, but how we ſhall eſcape it. Grievous is the torment of the damned for the bitterneſs of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but it is more grievous for the diverſitie of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118403:17"/>but moſt grievous for the eternity of the puniſhments. Ah, conſider before it be too late! what a ſad thing tis for ſouls, at laſt, to have the gate of Mercy, the gate of Indulgence, the gate of Hope, the gate of Glory, ſhut upon them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.10. When a ſinner is in hell, ſhall another Chriſt be found to dye for him? or will the ſame Chriſt be crucified again? Oh no; oh that you were ſo wiſe and merciful to your own ſouls,
<note place="margin">They were wont to ſay in former times, (<hi>Caius Seius bonus vir, ſed Chriſtianus. Caius Seius</hi> was a good man, but he was a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. You may eaſily apply it, &amp;c.</note> as to dwell upon theſe Scriptures, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Jeſus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, and ſaid unto him, Verily, verily, I ſay unto thee, except a man be born again, he cannot ſee the kingdom of God.</hi> Except men be firſt unmade, and new made up again by the Spirit and Word; except the whole frame of their old converſation be diſſolved, and a better erected, there is no heaven to be had. Heaven is too holy, and too hot to hold Drunkards, Revilers, Mockers, and ſuch like, as you may plainly ſee by comparing theſe Scriptures together, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20, 21. <hi>Jude</hi> 14, 15. <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.8. &amp; 22.15. He that is truth it ſelf and cannot lye, hath ſaid, <hi>Without holineſs no man ſhall ſee God,</hi> Heb. 12.14. This I am ſure of, that all mans happineſs here, is his holineſs, and his holineſs,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſtem</hi> cals ſome holy men of his time <hi>(aggelous)</hi> earthly angels.</note> ſhall hereafter be his happineſs. You muſt in this life be holy, or in the life to come you ſhall never be happy. <hi>Seneca,</hi> a heathen man, ſaw ſo much excellency that morality put upon a man, that he ſaith, that (<hi>ipſe aſpectus boni viri delectat</hi>) the very looks of a good man delights one. Oh then, what a beauty and glory, doth real ſanctity put upon a man; <hi>it makes him more excellent then his neighbour,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 12.26. When <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> heard the king of <hi>Perſia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm</hi> 16.3.</note> ſtiled the great king, ſaith he, <hi>I acknowledg none more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then my ſelf, unleſs more righteous; none greater, unleſs better.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to haſten towards a cloſe, you may be very confident of theſe few things, which I deſire, as you tender your own good, you would ſeriouſly conſider.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That thoſe waies of the fleſh, wherein now you walk, will be bitterneſs in the latter end,
<note place="margin">It was the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſinneth, doth in that decline from his purpoſed end, and is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Hark Scholer, ſaid the Harlot to <hi>Apulſius,</hi> 'Tis but a bitter ſweet that you are ſo fond of. Ah, your ſcoff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, will prove but a bitter ſweet at laſt. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.38, 39. &amp; chap. 9.4, 5. Conſtantine the great Symbole, was <hi>(immedicabile vulnus enſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcindendum eſt.)</hi> When there is no hope of curing, men muſt fall a cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And ſo will God deal with ſinners ſouls. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore look a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 40.15. I laugh ſaid <hi>Caligula</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Conſuls, to think that I can kill you with a nod of my head. And can't God do it with as much eaſe; <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.19. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, That in the cauſe of God he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <hi>(totius mundi odium &amp; impetum ſuſtinere)</hi> to undergo, the hatred and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence of the whole world. The Heathen Orator could ſay, <hi>(A recta conſcientia ne latum quidem unguem diſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum)</hi> a man may not depart an hairs breadth all his life long, from the dictates of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Pſa</hi> 63.1, 2, 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14 1. &amp; chap. 15.1. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3, 4. <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.24. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.39.60. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.12, 13, 14, 15. <hi>Tully</hi> ſaid of <hi>Caeſar (nihil ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liviſci ſoles, niſi injurias)</hi> That he forgat no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries.</note> 
               <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.12. <hi>There is a way which ſeemeth right unto a man; but the end thereof are the waies of death.</hi> Though ſin doth come ſometimes cloathed with a ſhew of reaſon, and religion, yet the end of it will be death.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118403:17"/>Sin at laſt will betray your ſouls into the hands of Satan, as <hi>Dalilah</hi> did <hi>Sampſon,</hi> into the hands of the Philiſtims. Sinne makes the ſoul black with filth, and red with guilt, and then vengeance follows. The Rabbins were wont to tell their Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, to ſcare them from ſin, that every ſin made Gods head ake; but, without ſound repentance, you will at laſt finde, that every ſin will make your hearts ake. Oh, that when you are tempted to ſin, you would ſay, as <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> the Oratour, did of the beautiful <hi>Lais,</hi> when he was asked an exceſſive ſum of money to behold her; I will not (ſaid he) buy repentance ſo dear. I am not ſo ill a merchant, as to ſell the eternal for the temporal.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You may be confident, that all your oppoſitions, one way or other, againſt the waies of God, and againſt the people of God, is a fighting againſt God, who will be too hard for you, when you have done your worſt; and what you get, you may put in your eyes, and weep it out again. Thoſe that ſtrive for maſtery with God, God will over-maſter with a witneſſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.4. <hi>who would ſet the briars and thornes againſt me in battel? I would go through them, I will burn them together.</hi> God can nod a ſoul to hell; He can ſpeak a ſoul miſerable in a moment. Who ever ſtood out againſt him and proſpered? There is ſuch a neer union between God and his people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and his waies, that you cannot poſſibly oppoſe them, but you oppoſe God himſelf, who can preſently cauſe the greateſt arm of humane power, to ſhrink up; as you may ſee in his dealing with <hi>Pharoah, Hamman, Belſhazzar,</hi> and others, &amp;c. Is a dry Reed able to ſtand againſt a conſuming fire? Is a worm able to overcom a Lion? Is weakneſs able to overcom ſtrength? <hi>Behold, the nations are as a drop of a bucket, and are counted as the ſmall duſt of the ballance: Behold, he taketh up the Iſles as a very little thing;</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks. And what then is the poor creature, that he ſhould fight againſt an Almighty Creator? <hi>Caeſar</hi> told <hi>Metellus,</hi> he could as eaſily deſtroy him, as bid it be done. So can God; Who dares then engage againſt him?</p>
            <p n="3">3. You may be confident, that though I hate your ſins, yet I do don't hate your perſons. I am willing to live in love,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118403:18"/>and peace with all men, ſo far as I may without ſin; but I abhor compliancy with any man, to the diſhonour of Chriſt, to the wounding of my conſcience, to the prophaning of holy things; or to the prejudice and diſadvantage of the truth. 'Tis below humanity to hate a man, whoſe nature and ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude he may behold in the humanity of Chriſt. (<hi>Deum odit qui hominem odit</hi>) He hateth God, that hateth man. I muſt love men, but hate their vice. It is ſaid of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> That they hated the deeds of the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> their errors not their perſons. So <hi>Jacob</hi> curſed the wrath of his ſons, but bleſſed their perſons. So <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. and ſo do I, through free mercy.</p>
            <p n="4">4. You may be confident, that I don't refuſe the baptizing of your children, and the giving you the Sacrament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> out of pride, or envy, or upon any carnal account in the world, but onely upon the grounds, that I have before laid down. I take the ſearcher of all hearts to witneſſe, that I ſhould much rejoyce and bleſſe the Lord, if he would be pleaſed to work ſuch a thorow work of grace upon all your hearts, as that I might (without ſinne) diſpence all the precious things of Chriſt to you. Ah, tis not a joy, but a real grief to my ſoul, that others han't that right, and can't come to thoſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, which God hath made ſo ſweet and advantagious to me, and many others of the ſons of Sion.</p>
            <p>Oh! how willing ſhould I be, and thoſe that walk with me, to give you the right-hand of Fellowſhip, if we could but ſee, that the Lord has taken you into fellowſhip with his bleſſed Self; that ſo the Ordinance might be a cordial, and not poyſon to you.</p>
            <p>I do profeſſe before the Lord, that I do, from my ſoul, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give you the wrong and injuries that you have done me, or attempted to do. God has been good to me, notwithſtanding my failing towards him, and my ſins againſt him: And the ſenſe of his love and rich goodneſs, makes my bowels to earn towards you.</p>
            <p>Oh! 'Tis a mercy more worth then a world to me, that God hath given me ſuch a frame of ſpirit, as that I can pray for your ſouls, and weep over your ſins; and that I am ready to ſerve you in all thoſe waies, wherein I may further
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118403:18"/>the eternall welfare of your ſouls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lihnod lelam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,</hi> Wee therefore learn that we may teach, is a Proverb a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Rabbins. I could have dealt with you in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, had I not intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the good of your ſouls. <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.15-<hi>ult. Acts</hi> 20.26, 27. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.17, 18, 19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.20, 21, 22. <hi>John</hi> 12.48. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>Micah</hi> 7.8, 9, 10. <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.9, 10, 11, 12. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17, 18. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 4, 5. Prayer is <hi>(porta coeli cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis paradiſi)</hi> the gate of Heaven, a key to let us in to Paradiſe. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.7-12. <hi>Nec Chriſtus nec coelum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur hyperbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len.</hi> A man cannot hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbolize in ſpeaking of Chriſt and Heaven. <hi>Omne bonum, in ſummo bono.</hi> All good is in the chiefeſt good. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.16, 17.</note> Make uſe of me in any thing wherein I may ſerve you without ſin, and ſee whether I ſhall not be willing to act for your good, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all provocations to the contrary.</p>
            <p n="5">5. For a cloſe (becauſe I would not be over tedious I ſhall draw many things within a narrow compaſſe) you may be confident that my end in writing, is your due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction and ſatisfaction, that you may weigh my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and clearly ſee that 'tis not will, nor humour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but Conſcience, Reaſon, and Religion, that acts me. If notwithſtanding what I have ſaid, you ſhall continue in your malice, envy, hatred, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall have comfort in this, that I have in all faithfullneſſe freed my ſelfe from being guilty of the blood of your ſouls; and in that I have declared to all the world my willingneſſe to ſerve the intereſt of your ſouls in all chings wherein I may without ſin. And moſt confident I am, that if what I have written do not better you, it will be a witneſſe againſt you, when you and I ſhall meet before Chriſts judgement ſeat. And confident I am, that God will bring much good to me out of all the plots, deſigns, and actings that have been, or that ſhall be by vain men againſt me. And confident I am, that, the more you ſtir in any way of baſeneſſe or wickedneſſe, the more the Lord will make you to ſtink, and the more contempt he will pour upon you, and the more bright he will cauſe my innocency to ſhine, and the more weighty ſhall be my Crowne in the day of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>My deſires for you before the Lord, are theſe, That you may have ſuch a ſight of your ſins as may work you to kiſſe the Son leſt he be angry, and you periſh when his wrath is kindled but a little. And that you may not trifle away the day of grace, and the things that belong to your eternall peace, leaſt God ſhould ſwear in his wrath, that you ſhall never enter into his reſt. Oh that in the light of the Spirit you may ſee Chriſt to be the greateſt good, the moſt deſire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able good, the moſt neceſſary good, the moſt ſuitable good, to be a totall good, an only good, and an eternall good;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118403:19"/>that ſo your ſouls may in good earneſt fall in love with Chriſt, and may cry out with that Martyr, <hi>None but Chriſt, none but Chriſt;</hi> Oh none but Chriſt to ſave us, and none but Chriſt to rule us, none but Chriſt to juſtifie us, and none but Chriſt to command us. Oh that you may ceaſe from doing evill, and learn to do well, that ſo you may be happy in life, bleſſed in death, and glorious in the morning of the Reſurrection.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:118403:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
